<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<chapter>
  <title>
    Conjunctions
  </title>

  <para>
    A conjunction is a word that joins other words, phrases, parts of
    sentences, or sentences together.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <title>
      Common Conjunctions:
    </title>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
	and
      </term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Usually joins two positive or two negative ideas.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>
	but
      </term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Used to connect two opposing statements.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>
	or
      </term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Provides a choice between ideas.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>
	so
      </term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Demonstrates an effect or a result, similar to
	  <emphasis>then</emphasis> in an
	  <code>if&#47;then</code> statement.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <section id="conjunctions_tutorial">
    <title>Transforming Conjunctions into Simple Sentences</title>

    <para>
      Conjunctions are an important part of effective writing, but
      they add complexity to sentence structure. When writing
      technical documentation, analyze whether a conjunction makes a
      sentence more or less clear than two separate statements.      
    </para>

    <para>
      This sentence can be understood, eventually, but it's
      confusing&#58;
    </para>

    <informalexample>
    <para>
      Foo2Bar is a framework that makes it easy to create application
      images, and takes application source code as an input, and
      produces a new image that runs the assembled application in an
      isolated sandbox.
    </para>
    </informalexample>
    
    <para> See how much clearer it is when written as three
    separate sentences&#58;
    </para>

    <informalexample>
    <para>
      Foo2Bar is a framework that makes it easy to create application
      images. It takes application source code to produce an
      executable image. Foo2Bar images run in an isolated sandbox for
      increased security.
    </para>
    </informalexample>
    
    <para>
      Another example&#58;
    </para>

    <informalexample>
    <para>
      To distribute your modifications, gather the configuration
      files, documentation files, all build materials, including build
      scripts and scripts needed to dynamically generate makefiles,
      and compiled binaries, and create a tar archive, or use the
      <command>foopkg</command> command on the parent directory.
    </para>
    </informalexample>
    
    <para>
      This becomes much clearer when rewritten with fewer
      conjunctions&#58;
    </para>

    <informalexample>
    <para>
      There are two ways to distribute your modifications. You can
      create a tar archive manually or you can use the
      <command>foopkg</command> command. For each, you must include
      all compiled binaries, configuration files, documentation, build
      scripts, and scripts to dynamically generate makefiles.
    </para>
    </informalexample>
  </section>
  
  <section id="conjunctions_tutorial_choose">
    <title>Choosing the Right Conjunctions</title>

    <para>
      Sometimes conjunctions are the right choice, and in those cases
      you must choose the correct conjunction. 
    </para>

    <bridgehead>But</bridgehead>
    
    <para>
      The <emphasis>but</emphasis> conjunction is very inflexible. It
      is appropriate when the two statements being connected are
      exclusive of one another, These
      two examples have very different meanings&#58;
    </para>

    <informalexample>
      <para>
	A car can drive but it cannot fly.
      </para>
    </informalexample>

    <para>
      Most importantly, <emphasis>but</emphasis> implies that two
      statements are opposed even if they are not. Using
      <emphasis>but</emphasis> incorrectly confuses readers. For
      example, if you write&#58;
    </para>

    <informalexample>
      <para>
	Linux is open source but it is a stable, Enterprise-ready
	platform.
      </para>
    </informalexample>

    <para>
      A reader probably interprets it to mean that Linux is
      Enterprise-ready <emphasis>in spite of</emphasis> it being open
      source. What you actually mean is that Linux is
      <emphasis>both</emphasis> open source and Enterprise-ready.
    </para>

    <informalexample>
      <para>
	Linux is open source and is a stable, Enterprise-ready
	platform.
      </para>
    </informalexample>
    

    <bridgehead>And</bridgehead>

    <para>
      The <emphasis>and</emphasis> conjunction connects two equally
      true or equally false statements into one&#58;
    </para>

    <informalexample>
      <para>
	That hat is not red and it is not mine.
      </para>

      <para>
	This fedora is red and it is mine.
      </para>
    </informalexample>

    
    <bridgehead>Or</bridgehead>

    <para>
      The <emphasis>or</emphasis> conjunction implies a choice between
      the two statements it connects&#58;
    </para>

    <informalexample>
      <para>
	Run the <application>DHCP</application> daemon embedded on the
	router or run your own on a server.
      </para>
    </informalexample>
    
    <para>
      In the preceding statement, it's significant that you can use
      either the embedded DHCP server or your own, because using both
      could cause conflicts severe enough to bring down your
      network. It would be inaccurate to use a different conjunction&#58;
    </para>

    <informalexample>
      <para>
	Run the <application>DHCP</application> daemon embedded on the
	router and run your own on a server.
      </para>
    </informalexample>

    <para>
      In fact, for added emphasis, you can use
      <emphasis>either</emphasis>&#58;
    </para>

    <informalexample>
      <para>
	Run either the <application>DHCP</application> daemon embedded
	on the router or run your own on a server.
      </para>
    </informalexample>

    
    <bridgehead>So</bridgehead>

    <para>
      The <emphasis>so</emphasis> conjunction connects causes and
      effects&#58;
    </para>

    <informalexample>
      <para>
	&RHELX; is the latest release. This server is running &RHEL6;, so it needs to be updated.
      </para>
    
      <para>
	This server is not running firewalld or SELinux, so it does not pass my security audit.  
      </para>
    </informalexample>
  </section>
  
  <section id="conjunctions_exercise">
    <title>Exercise</title>

    <para>
      Practice using the correct conjunction, or rewrite to use
      no conjunction&#58;
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Linux is an excellent platform for development, but it is an
	  excellent platform for deployment.
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Security-enhanced Linux (SELinux) is an implementation of a
	  mandatory access control mechanism in the Linux kernel. It is an
	  important part of system security. Do not disable SELinux, so
	  use the <command>setenforce</command> command to put SELinux
	  into permissive mode temporarily.
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Click the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button to proceed to the
	  next screen, and then click the <guilabel>Name</guilabel> link
	  in the upper-left corner of the page or the
	  <guilabel>Name</guilabel> selection in the
	  <guilabel>Navigation</guilabel> drop-down menu in the
	  upper-right corner of the page, and click the
	  <guibutton>arrow</guibutton> icon to continue.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  
</chapter>
