<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "English_for_Techies.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chap-Documentation-English_for_Techies-_Lists_and_Tables_">
	<title> Lists and Tables </title>
	 <para>
		There is no single standard for writing a list. The style of each list depends on the contents of the list, but the style should remain consistent within each list.
	</para>
	 <para>
		There are, broadly, three different types of lists: the ordered list, the itemized list, and the variable list. When a reader must follow the items in a list sequentially, use an ordered list. If sequence is not important, use an itemized list. When defining a list of terms, use the variable list.
	</para>
	 <section id="sect-Documentation-English_for_Techies-_Lists_and_Tables_-Stems">
		<title>Stems</title>
		 <para>
			Avoid using bullet point lists to format a single sentence. Some translation tools, for example Zanata, display list items and the introductory sentence (or <emphasis>sentence stem</emphasis>) as individual sentences for translation. If these are not complete sentences, they are difficult to translate.
		</para>
		 <table>
			<title></title>
			 <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
				<colspec colname="c1"></colspec>
				 <colspec colname="c2"></colspec>
				 <thead>
					<row>
						<entry> Example </entry>
						 <entry> Improvement </entry>

					</row>

				</thead>
				 <tbody>
					<row>
						<entry> <para>
							Before you start the installation, make sure you have
						</para>
						 <itemizedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									enough free storage on your system
								</para>

							</listitem>
							 <listitem>
								<para>
									backed up any data that you want to keep
								</para>

							</listitem>

						</itemizedlist>
						 <para>
							to ensure a smooth installation.
						</para>
						 </entry>
						 <entry> <para>
							Before you start the installation, follow these steps to ensure a smooth installation:
						</para>
						 <itemizedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Ensure you have enough free storage on your system.
								</para>

							</listitem>
							 <listitem>
								<para>
									Back up any data that you want to keep.
								</para>

							</listitem>

						</itemizedlist>
						 </entry>

					</row>

				</tbody>

			</tgroup>

		</table>

	</section>
	 <section id="sect-Documentation-English_for_Techies-_Lists_and_Tables_-Punctuation">
		<title>Punctuation</title>
		 <para>
			If you place a period at the end of one list item in a list, then use a period at the end of each list item in that list.
		</para>
		 <para>
			Use punctuation when a list item completes an introductory sentence.
		</para>
		 <informalexample> <para>
			Before removing your USB hard drive from your computer, you may need to:
		</para>
		 <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					close any open files located on the drive.
				</para>

			</listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>
					close any terminal open to a directory on the drive.
				</para>

			</listitem>

		</itemizedlist>
		 </informalexample> <para>
			Use punctuation when a list item contains more than one complete sentence.
		</para>
		 <informalexample> <para>
			Before removing your USB hard drive from your computer, there are two tasks you may need to take.
		</para>
		 <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					If you are running an application with a files from the drive open, you must close the file. Alternately, save a new copy of the file to some other location. If you are not sure whether you have any files from the drive open, use the <command>lsof</command> command.
				</para>

			</listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>
					If you have a terminal open to a directory on the drive, either close the terminal or change directory to a directory not located on the drive.
				</para>

			</listitem>

		</itemizedlist>
		 </informalexample> <para>
			Do not use punctuation for:
		</para>
		 <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					sentence fragments
				</para>

			</listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>
					single words or short terms
				</para>

			</listitem>

		</itemizedlist>
		 <para>
			Most of all, strive for consistency. If a list contains two list items that are complete sentences, and a third that is just a single word, you should restructure your list. For example, change the single word list item into a simple sentence so that it matches the other items. Alternately, review whether the items in your list belong in a list together.
		</para>

	</section>
	 <section id="sect-Documentation-English_for_Techies-_Lists_and_Tables_-Tense">
		<title>Tense</title>
		 <para>
			Retain the same verb tense for each list item.
		</para>
		 <para>
			For example, this is incorrect:
		</para>
		 <informalexample> <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Students gain an understanding of the Linux init system.
				</para>

			</listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>
					All students will learn how to use <command>systemctl</command>.
				</para>

			</listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>
					Students create a simple chroot for testing.
				</para>

			</listitem>

		</itemizedlist>
		 </informalexample> <para>
			The second list item uses the future tense, while the other two are present tense.
		</para>
		 <para>
			This is correct:
		</para>
		 <informalexample> <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Gain an understanding of the Linux init system.
				</para>

			</listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>
					Learn how to use the <command>systemctl</command> command to start, stop, and monitor services.
				</para>

			</listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>
					Create a simple chroot for testing.
				</para>

			</listitem>

		</itemizedlist>
		 </informalexample> <para>
			This is called <emphasis>parallelism</emphasis>, and should be applied across all lists within the same book.
		</para>
		 <para>
			A list that constantly changes sentence structure is confusing:
		</para>
		 <informalexample> <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Use to specify the X variable.
				</para>

			</listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>
					Specifies which value to apply to Y.
				</para>

			</listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>
					You can use this to change the config from a POSIX shell.
				</para>

			</listitem>

		</itemizedlist>
		 </informalexample> <para>
			It is easier to understand when a list maintains the same voice throughout. A reader might refer to several lists or tables within a book, so ensuring a consistent voice in every list or table helps readers quickly parse important information.
		</para>

	</section>
	 <section id="sect-Documentation-English_for_Techies-_Lists_and_Tables_-Key_Value_Lists">
		<title>Key-Value Lists</title>
		 <para>
			If you are writing a list that exists only to define terms, use a variable list.
		</para>
		 <informalexample> <variablelist>
			<varlistentry id="varl-Documentation-English_for_Techies-Key_Value_Lists-example.com">
				<term>example.com</term>
				 <listitem>
					<para>
						A domain reserved as a safe example URL. This is the correct way to define a term in a list.
					</para>

				</listitem>

			</varlistentry>
			 <varlistentry id="varl-Documentation-English_for_Techies-Key_Value_Lists-example.local">
				<term>example.local</term>
				 <listitem>
					<para>
						A domain that exists only within a local network.
					</para>

				</listitem>

			</varlistentry>
			 <varlistentry id="varl-Documentation-English_for_Techies-Key_Value_Lists-cat">
				<term>cat</term>
				 <listitem>
					<para>
						The concatenate command.
					</para>

				</listitem>

			</varlistentry>

		</variablelist>
		 </informalexample> <para>
			Sometimes your list definitions do not contain exclusively simple terms to be defined, so you have to use an itemized list to allow for mixed list items. Delimiters separating a term from its definition can be confused as being a part of the term, so it is best to define terms in complete sentences, and with appropriate Docbook tags.
		</para>
		 <informalexample> <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="strong">example.com</emphasis> is a domain reserved as a safe example URL. This is the correct way to define a term in a list.
				</para>

			</listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="strong">example.local</emphasis>: a domain that exists only within a local network. This is not as clean, since the colon (:) could be interpreted as part of the term being defined.
				</para>

			</listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>
					<command>cat</command> - the concatenate command. This is also unclear, since the dash (-) could represent shorthand for POSIX <systemitem>stdin</systemitem>.
				</para>

			</listitem>

		</itemizedlist>
		 </informalexample>
	</section>
	 <section id="sect-Documentation-English_for_Techies-_Lists_and_Tables_-Tables">
		<title>Tables</title>
		 <para>
			Tables are, essentially, lists rendered horizontally as well as vertically.
		</para>
		 <para>
			The same rules apply for tables as for lists, with the primary goal being internal consistency. This table is not consistent:
		</para>
		 <informaltable>
			<tgroup cols="3">
				<colspec align="left" colwidth="6em"></colspec>
				 <colspec align="left" colwidth="6em"></colspec>
				 <colspec align="left" colwidth="16em"></colspec>
				 <thead>
					<row>
						<entry> Server </entry>
						 <entry> OS </entry>
						 <entry> Function </entry>

					</row>

				</thead>
				 <tbody>
					<row>
						<entry><emphasis role="strong">servera</emphasis></entry>
						 <entry>RHEL&nbsp;7</entry>
						 <entry>DNS</entry>

					</row>
					 <row>
						<entry><emphasis role="strong">serverb</emphasis></entry>
						 <entry>RHEL&nbsp;7</entry>
						 <entry>DNS fallback</entry>

					</row>
					 <row>
						<entry><emphasis role="strong">serverc</emphasis></entry>
						 <entry>Fedora&nbsp;26</entry>
						 <entry>This is only a testing server.</entry>

					</row>

				</tbody>

			</tgroup>

		</informaltable>
		 <para>
			This is a consistent table:
		</para>
		 <informaltable>
			<tgroup cols="3">
				<colspec align="left" colwidth="6em"></colspec>
				 <colspec align="left" colwidth="6em"></colspec>
				 <colspec align="left" colwidth="16em"></colspec>
				 <thead>
					<row>
						<entry> Server </entry>
						 <entry> OS </entry>
						 <entry> Function </entry>

					</row>

				</thead>
				 <tbody>
					<row>
						<entry><emphasis role="strong">servera</emphasis></entry>
						 <entry>RHEL&nbsp;7</entry>
						 <entry>DNS</entry>

					</row>
					 <row>
						<entry><emphasis role="strong">serverb</emphasis></entry>
						 <entry>RHEL&nbsp;7</entry>
						 <entry>DNS fallback</entry>

					</row>
					 <row>
						<entry><emphasis role="strong">serverc</emphasis></entry>
						 <entry>Fedora&nbsp;26</entry>
						 <entry>This is only a testing server</entry>

					</row>

				</tbody>

			</tgroup>

		</informaltable>
		 <para>
			Even though the final entry in the table is a complete sentence, it has no period at the end of the sentence to better match the convention established by previous entries.
		</para>

	</section>

</chapter>

