<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<chapter>
  <title>
    Using the right possessive 
  </title>

  <para>
    The possessive form indicates ownership. Nouns and pronouns have possessive forms.
  </para>

  <section id="possessive_nouns">
    <title>
      Converting nouns into possessive nouns
    </title>
    
  <para>
    These are the different rules for converting nouns into their possessive forms&#58;
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
	Add <emphasis>&#39;s</emphasis> to singular nouns:
      </term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  An <emphasis>administrators&#39;s</emphasis> computer.
	</para>
	<para>
	  A software <emphasis>project&#39;s</emphasis> blog.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
	Add a lone <emphasis>&#39;</emphasis> to the end of a plural noun that all ready ends in <emphasis>s</emphasis>:
      </term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Update all of the <emphasis>students&#39;</emphasis> computers.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Email each of the <emphasis>projects&#39;</emphasis> reports to the project manager.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
	Treat plural nouns that do not end in <emphasis>s</emphasis> the same as a singular noun&#58;
      </term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Install Linux on all of the <emphasis>children&#39;s</emphasis> computers.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Bring those <emphasis>people&#39;s</emphasis> laptops in for repair.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
	If a noun is compound, convert only the final noun to its possessive form&#58;
      </term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Install Linux on <emphasis>admin and manager&#39;s</emphasis> computers.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Bring the <emphasis>student and teachers&#39;</emphasis> laptops in for repair.
	</para>
      </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  </section>

  <section id="possessive_pronouns">
    <title>
      Converting pronouns into possessive pronouns
    </title>

  <para>
    Pronouns have their own special possessive forms, separate from their root words. In technical writing, the gender neutral ones are the most common&#58;
  </para>

  <para>
    For personal ownership in the third person, use <emphasis>their</emphasis>, whether it refers to a singular or plural noun&#58;
  </para>

  <informalexample>
    <para>
      Give your user a GPG key so that their email can be encrypted.
    </para>

    <para>
      Give all of your users GPG keys so that their emails can be encrypted.
    </para>
  </informalexample>

  <para>
    For personal ownership in the second person, use <emphasis>your</emphasis>&#58;
  </para>

    <informalexample>
    <para>
      Do not give your password to anyone.
    </para>
    </informalexample>
    
  <para>
    If a pronoun refers to a nonhuman, use <emphasis>its</emphasis>&#58;
  </para>

  <informalexample>
    <para>
      Post the checksum of an RPM so its integrity is verifiable by users.
    </para>
  </informalexample>

  <para>
    The plural form of <emphasis>its</emphasis> is also <emphasis>their</emphasis>&#58;
  </para>

  <informalexample>
    <para>
      Post the checksums of all your RPM packages so that their integrity is verifiable.
    </para>
  </informalexample>

  <section id="possessive_its">
    <title>
      Using <emphasis>its</emphasis> and <emphasis>it&#39;s</emphasis>
    </title>

    <para>
      The words <emphasis>its</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>it&#39;s</emphasis> notoriously get confused for one
      another in writing. You don&#39;t think about the words when you
      speak, because they're pronounced exactly the same way, but when
      you write them, it matters which one you use.
    </para>

    <para>
      There are two simple rules you can use to remember which to use&#58;
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The word <emphasis>it&#39;s</emphasis>, like all contractions, is a combination of two words&#58; <emphasis>it</emphasis> and <emphasis>is</emphasis>. Whenever you see <emphasis>it&#39;s</emphasis> in a sentence, replace it with <emphasis>it is</emphasis>. If it does not make sense, then it is not used correctly. For example&#58;
	</para>

	<informalexample>
	  <para>
	    Open the computer and re-seat it&#39;s RAM.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    Open the computer and re-seat it is RAM.
	  </para>
	</informalexample>

	<para>
	  In this example, it makes no sense to say &#34;re-seat it is RAM.&#34; Obviously, the writer intended to use <emphasis>its</emphasis>. 
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  In technical documentation, contractions are generally avoided. Use <emphasis>its</emphasis> as a possessive pronoun, and use <emphasis>it is</emphasis> instead of <emphasis>it&#39;s</emphasis>.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    
    <para>
      The following <command>grep</command> statement checks for <emphasis>it&#39;s</emphasis> in a file&#58;
    </para>

    <screen>
      <prompt>&#38;</prompt> <command>grep</command> <option>-iE</option> &#34;it&#39;s&#34; <filename>filename.xml</filename>
    </screen>

  </section>
  <section id="possessive_its">
    <title>
      Using <emphasis>your</emphasis> and <emphasis>you&#39;re</emphasis>
    </title>

    <para>
      The words <emphasis>your</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>you&#39;re</emphasis> also get confused for one
      another in writing. 
    </para>

    <para>
      The same rules about <emphasis>its</emphasis> and <emphasis>it&#39;s</emphasis> apply to <emphasis>your</emphasis> and <emphasis>you&#39;re</emphasis>. To reiterate&#58;
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The word <emphasis>you&#39;re</emphasis>, like all
	  contractions, is a combination of two words&#58;
	  <emphasis>you</emphasis> and
	  <emphasis>are</emphasis>. Whenever you see
	  <emphasis>you&#39;re</emphasis> in a sentence, replace it
	  with <emphasis>you are</emphasis>. If it does not make
	  sense, then it is not used correctly&#58;
	</para>

	<informalexample>
	  <para>
	    To get the most out of a Linux desktop, replace <emphasis>you&#39;re</emphasis> single-button mouse with a three-button mouse.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    To get the most out of a Linux desktop, replace <emphasis>you are</emphasis> single-button mouse with a three-button mouse.
	  </para>
	</informalexample>
	<para>
	  In this example, it makes no sense to say &#34;you are single-button mouse.&#34; Obviously, the writer intended to use <emphasis>your</emphasis>. 
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  In technical documentation, contractions are generally avoided. Use <emphasis>your</emphasis> as a possessive pronoun, and use <emphasis>you are</emphasis> instead of <emphasis>you&#39;re</emphasis>.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    
    <para>
      The following <command>grep</command> statement checks for <emphasis>you&#39;re</emphasis> in a file&#58;
    </para>

    <screen>
      <prompt>&#38;</prompt> <command>grep</command> <option>-iE</option> &#34;you&#39;re&#34; <filename>filename.xml</filename>
    </screen>

  </section>

</section>

  <section id="possessive_exercise">
    <title>
      Exercise
    </title>

    <para>
      Rewrite these sentences, as needed, using the correct possessive forms&#58;
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Press the <guibutton>Enter</guibutton> key to convert the file and view it on its screen.
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Linux and BSD both use monolithic kernels as its basis.
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The library's and binary's maintainer forgot to upload the packages.  
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Have each user activate two-factor authentication on his account.
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  You must use <application>mutt</application> as the email client.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  </chapter>
