<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<chapter>
  <title>
    Pronouns
  </title>

  <para>
    Pronouns are pointers to a noun. These are some common singular pronouns&#58;
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	you
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	it
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	this
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	that
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
    These are some common plural pronouns&#58;
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	they
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	these
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	those
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
    In technical writing, pronouns are simplified because English
    doesn't assign gender to inorganic things.
  </para>

  <note>
    <para>
      If you are writing a use case and need to reference a fictional
      human, use generic terms such as a job title, like systems
      administrator or programmer, rather than an arbitrary name like
      &#34;John&#34; or &#34;Jane&#34;. Use the pronoun &#34;they&#34;
      instead of &#34;him&#34; or &#34;her&#34;.
    </para>
  </note>
  
  <section id="pronouns_tutorial">
    <title>How to Use Pronouns</title>

  <para>
    For pronouns to work as designed, they require two things&#58;
  </para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	The reader must know what noun the pronoun references.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	The tense of the pronoun and its noun and verb must match.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>
    Here are some examples&#58;
  </para>

  
  <bridgehead>Singular noun</bridgehead>

  <informalexample>
    <para>
      When referring back to a singular noun, use the pronoun
      <emphasis>it</emphasis>. For example&#58;
    </para>
  </informalexample>

  <informalexample>
    <para>
      The server is running &RHEL7;, and it has 8 TB of storage.
    </para>	
  </informalexample>

  
  <bridgehead>Plural pronouns</bridgehead>

    <para>
      When referring back to a plural noun, use the pronoun
      <emphasis>they</emphasis>. For example&#58;
    </para>

    <informalexample>
      <para>
	Desktop computers often get used for office tasks, but they
	can also be configured as servers.
      </para>
    </informalexample>
    
      <bridgehead>Possessive pronouns</bridgehead>
      
      <para>
	To indicate that a pronoun possesses something, use
	the possessive form of the appropriate pronoun. For example&#58;
      </para>

      <informalexample>
	<para>
	  Emacs is a text editor, but its real power is its LISP
	  interpreter.
	</para>
      </informalexample>
      
      <para>
	The same applies for plural forms&#58;
      </para>

      <informalexample>
	<para>
	  Open source programmers are brave to subject their code to the
	  scrutiny of anyone who wants to look at it.
	</para>
      </informalexample>

      <para>
	You may have both singular and plural in a sentence&#58; 
      </para>
      
      <informalexample>
	<para>
	  Your colleagues may run Windows or MacOS on their computers,
	  but you should run Linux on yours.
	</para>
      </informalexample>

      
      <bridgehead>Pronouns in context</bridgehead>
      
      <para>
	Sometimes a pronoun is used in a separate sentence than the
	one establishing the noun being referenced. This relies on
	the reader to understand from context which noun the pronoun most
	likely refers to. 
      </para>

      <para>
	Sometimes it is very obvious&#58;
      </para>

      <informalexample>
	<para>
	  I like drinking coffee while I sit and type at my
	  computer. Sometimes, I even dunk a doughnut into it.
	</para>
      </informalexample>

      <para>
	In that phrase, the reader knows what &#34;it&#34; means
	from contextual clues. The writer means &#34;Sometimes, I
	dunk a doughnut into my coffee&#34;, not &#34;Sometimes,
	I dunk a doughnut into my computer.&#34;
      </para>

      <para>
	Sometimes it is less obvious&#58;
      </para>

      <informalexample>
	<para>
	  The <command>foo</command> command is being developed to
	  replace the <command>bar</command> command. It is installed
	  by default, and it has a bug in it that erases all of your
	  data permanently.
	</para>
      </informalexample>

      <para>
	In that paragraph, the reader cannot know definitively which
	command, <command>foo</command> or <command>bar</command>,
	erases all of their data and which command is safe to
	use. Sometimes, using a pronoun is not as effective as being
	explicit.
      </para>

      <para>
	Try rewriting the sample paragraph, assuming that
	<command>foo</command> is the dangerous command and that
	<command>bar</command> is the safe command.
      </para>
    
      <bridgehead>Verifying pronouns</bridgehead>

      <para>
	To verify that a pronoun makes sense, reread a sentence or
	paragraph, replacing the pronoun you chose with the subject&#58;
	For example&#58;
      </para>

      <informalexample>
	<para>
	  Desktop computers often get used for office tasks, but they
	  can also be configured as servers for a small network.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Desktop computers often get used for office tasks, but
	  desktop computers can also be configured as servers for a
	  small network.
	</para>	
      </informalexample>
      
      <para>
	If it does not make sense, or if it impossible to read back
	with its subject replaced because there is no indication of
	what the correct subject is, then the pronoun has not been
	used correctly.
      </para>

      <informalexample>
	<para>
	  The <command>foo</command> command is being developed to
	  replace the <command>bar</command> command. It is installed
	  by default, and it has a bug in it that erases all of your
	  data permanently.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The <command>foo</command> command is being developed to
	  replace the <command>bar</command> command. <emphasis>Foo?
	  Bar?</emphasis> is installed by default, and <emphasis>foo?
	  bar?</emphasis> has a bug in <emphasis>foo? bar?</emphasis>
	  that erases all of your data permanently.
	</para>
      </informalexample>

      <para> If it still says what you meant to say, then you have
      placed the pronoun in the correct place. Here is an example
      using a plural pronoun&#58;
      </para>

      <informalexample>
	<para>
	  Pronouns are like variables. They hold whatever information the author places into them.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Pronouns are like variables. Pronouns and variables hold
	  whatever information the author places into pronouns and
	  variables.
	</para>
      </informalexample>
      
  </section>

  <section id="pronouns_exercise">
    <title>Exercise</title>

    <para>
      Correct these pronouns as needed&#58;
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The systems administrators imaged the computers so that
	  its host names followed a logical naming scheme.
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Return the laptop to the store and get refunded for them.
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Okular is the best PDF viewer on the market. Admittedly,
	  it's not the best format for digital releases compared to
	  EPUB, but it's great for printing.
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The systems administrators imaged each computer so that
	  its host name followed a logical naming scheme.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
      
  </section>
</chapter>
